Now today's דף daf is דף ד daf dalet and we pick
up at the bottom of ג עמוד ב gimmel amud bet and
the current topic under discussion, I mean this debate of רבה Rabbah
and רבא Rava which is still going to last us for a
few days, which is whether the reason for the משנה Mishna that
the שליח shaliach says, whoever is the one who delivers the גט
get says בפני נכתב ובפני נחתם, bifnai nichtav ubifnai nichtam, it was
signed and sealed in front of me, is he basically need to
testify that it was done according to the הלכה, halacha, which or
specifically the הלכה halacha of לשמה, lishma, which is רבה's Rabbah opinion,
or was it that it was in order to validate the signatures
so if the גט get ever gets challenged in the future it
should not be difficult, it should not, they should not have to
face the challenge of the difficulty of finding people who recognize and
can validate the signatures, that's עדים מצויים לקיימו. edim metzuyim lekaymo. And
as the גמרא Gemara has really pointed out,
there are two words, there are two things he's claiming: written and
signed. So signed seems to support the idea that it's about knowing
who the signatories are or and knowing that it was properly signed,
and written seems to emphasize the idea that it was followed the
הלכות halachot of how a גט get is supposed to be written.
So the question is: how does each position deal with the other
phrase? So רבא Rava who says it's about validating the signature said
that the person בפני נכתב, bifnai nichtav, the purpose of בפני נכתב
bifnai nichtav was just to signal that this is special, that this
is not a normal validation of signatures, because since this is really
only being done with one person, which is unusual, as the גמרא
Gemara explained, we normally need two people, two witnesses to validate signatures,
and so people should not get confused and misinformed or make mistakes
or whatever about how many people are needed to validate signatures, they
see that if the person is testifying to the fact that it
was also written in front of him, they realize that this is
something distinctive that is going on, it's unique to גיטין, Gittin, it's
not just about the signatures. So that's what רבא Rava said. But
for רבה Rabbah who says that it's a specific unique גט get
issue to testify that it was done properly, just say בפני נכתב,
bifnai nichtav, it was written. What is the purpose of emphasizing signed?
So the גמרא Gemara here assumes that it must be that רבה
Rabbah understands that the משנה Mishna which needs one to testify about
both being signed, written and signed, that the משנה Mishna follows a
position that demands that the laws of גיטין Gittin be followed and
there were special requirements of גט get be followed not only in
the writing but even in the signing. And this is and therefore
it wants to explore who is it that has these equal demands
in the writing and in the signing? And it puts out, and
is very helpful because it puts out for us right here on
yesterday's דף, daf, second דף daf in the מסכת, masechet, a fundamental
debate that is going to carry through for the rest of the
מסכת, masechet, which is basically what makes this piece of paper into
a גט. get. Is it the way it is, is it the
writing of it and it was written and followed the right הלכות
halachot and so on, or until it's signed it's just a piece
of paper? And it becomes a גט get when it is signed
and that turns it into a document that really speaks in the
voice of witnesses that carries weight and so on. And that it
sees as a debate between רבי אלעזר Rabbi Eliezer and רבי מאיר,
Rabbi Meir, and it sort of sees as a way of like
a way of testing that debate, when do you need this requirement
of מחובר, mechubar, of that it cannot be written when it is
attached to the ground. There cannot be anything between it becoming a
גט get and it being delivered. Okay, so רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir
says that really is only that there can't be anything between it
being signed and delivered. So for him it is really just the
signing of it that turns it into the גט, get, and that
is a phrase of עדי חתימה
edai
chatima or let's say חתימה chasima
in the אשכנז Ashkenaz and גמרא Gemara language כרתי. karti. Okay, so
the word כרתי karti is like the word כורת, koret, but you
have like כורת הברית koret habrit and you have כריתות, kritut, right?
So it like it cuts it, it makes it into the גט,
get, it makes it into that it is the signing that turns
it into the גט. get. So the requirement is and it's only
between its being signed and delivered that it cannot be attached to
the ground, but בדיעבד bediavad it could be attached to the ground
when it was being written. That's רבי מאיר. Rabbi Meir. As opposed
to רבי אלעזר, Rabbi Eliezer,
now being attached to the ground is not a great example there
because if it isn't attached to the ground when it's being written
it's also not going to be attached when it's being signed. So
what it uses for רבי אלעזר Rabbi Eliezer to demonstrate for him
the opposite, that the key is when it is being written, is
the point that he says that you do not need גט get
to be signed. Okay, he says that if you deliver a גט
get that is not signed, it is a כשר kosher גט, get,
provided that there, no, even לכתחילה, lechatchila, least it's כשר kosher even
מדרבנן mid'rabbanan at least, but maybe בדיעבד, bediavad, but no, it seems
even לכתחילה. lechatchila. Okay, because he says that you do not need
the signatures do not are not necessary to be part of the
גט. get. Okay, so that is a position of. Now, it does
not mean he doesn't need witnesses at all. Okay, he says you
need to deliver it in the presence of witnesses. Now here's an
interesting conceptual question within רבי אלעזר: Rabbi Eliezer: is it that he
needs it to be delivered in front of witnesses the same way
what else do you need to do in front of witnesses, similar
to גט? get?
What else is not a valid act unless it's done in front
of witnesses?
קידושין. Kiddushin. Right, if you give a ring to the, a man
gives a ring to woman not in front of witnesses, it's not
a good קידושין. Kiddushin. So one way of understanding his requirements for
there to be witnesses when the גט get is delivered is not
about the actual instrument of the גט. get. It is about the
need for witnesses to make גיטין gittin or קידושין Kiddushin valid, just
to test witness the act that is being done. The other way
to understand it is that he feels no, the witnesses actually also
somehow combine are part of making it into a גט, get, but
they still don't have to sign the גט, get, they just have
to be present. Okay, but that's what he says: עדי מסירה כרתי.
eidim mesira karti.
Okay, which means it's the ones who
witness the גט get being given. Okay, giving, given over.
Right, but signatures you would usually...
no, but but let's assume no signatures. Okay, well we're now the
next question is what happens when they do sign it? What does
that mean for רבי אליעזר? Rabbi Eliezer?
What happens if the husband's sending it with a שליח? shaliach?
Well, we'll get to...
yeah, go ahead... so he's not requiring that there were witnesses to
that original appointment?
That's an excellent question. Okay, do you need witnesses to be able
to testify to all the pieces to put them together, to know
that this guy was assigned as an agent by the husband or
not, or do you just need witnesses for the act of delivery?
Great question, I'm not going to answer it now. Okay, but I'm
saying that is a really really good question. Okay, so that is
what רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer says. Okay, so it does not need
signatures. Does not need signatures, but you do need but you do
need but you need okay you need witnesses for the delivery.
Witnesses for the delivery. Okay, that is what he says. And the
question is does that mean you need it just because it's an
act of divorce or does that mean that you need it in
order to create the actual object of the גט, get, they just
don't have to be signed. But now the גמרא Gemara but this
is the big debate. What turn do do the signatures turn it
into the גט get or not? So the גמרא Gemara says that
for רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir it's only the signatures. So why would
you have to and therefore all the requirements, the גמרא Gemara assumes
which is an amazing idea, if גט get is a piece of
paper until it's signed, so there's no logic that you could have
any demands on the writing of the גט. get. All the requirements
of לשמה lishma and so on are only on the signing. So
the סופר sofer writes it, you could just print it off of
your computer, you have nothing in mind, you're not thinking of this
particular women, you print off a million גיטין gittin with random different
names, doesn't matter. Oh, you're a שמעון Shimon and you want to
divorce a רחל? Rochel? Okay, here we go, here's the גט get
for you. Okay, and it means nothing until it is signed, and
therefore you would only have to testify at on the signing. And
for רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer the assumption is the witnesses are not
relevant to the גט, get, the witnesses are just part of witnessing
the act. So therefore there's no way you could demand any anything
to be done specifically uniquely like לשמה lishma requirements on the signing.
So who is it that has demands both on the writing and
the signing? That's the question. So that's a summary of yesterday or
a semi a few more minutes 'cause we we were a little
cut short for time at the end. And now let's pick up
at the bottom of ג' עמוד ב'. gimmel amud bet. It says
like this.
So the גמרא Gemara says שאין she-ein I'll pick up five lines
from the bottom and re-read one more line of רבי אליעזר's Rabbi
Eliezer quote: שאין העדים חותמין על הגט. she-ein ha-eidim chosmin al haget.
The witnesses do not sign the גט get according to רבי אליעזר,
Rabbi Eliezer, אלא מפני תיקון העולם, ella mipnei tikkun ha-olam, only in
order for the betterment of the community, of the society. Which means
what? Which means if you don't have it's hard to find those
witnesses that if you just have people standing and watching, you know
who knows if the woman's going to claim I was divorced and
they'll say prove it, right? So what are you going to do?
Go try to find who those people are who were standing and
watching the delivery? So it's helpful to have the גט get signed.
Okay, now the question is going to be but you know how
weighty are those signatures when they go ahead and do sign it,
right? What is the meaning of those signatures if they're not required?
Alright, so that's going to be something that we're going to look
at in a few minutes. So now the גמרא Gemara still wants
to know so who is it that requires both the writing and
the signing? ואלא ve-ella says the גמרא Gemara רבי מאיר היא. Rabbi
Meir hi. Fine, let's say רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir does make does
require the writing. Now how could he require the writing if it's
all about the signing? וכי לא בעי רבי מאיר כתיבה לשמה, ve-chi
lo ba Rabbi Meir ketiva lishma, when does he not demand that
the writing be done properly like or it doesn't have to you
know it doesn't have to be written on it can be written
even on a tree בדיעבד, bedi'avad, as long as it's signed when
it's cut down? So why when is that true? מדאורייתא, mid-oraita, biblically
speaking. But מדרבנן, mid-rabbanan, rabbinically, בעי. ba. Okay, so that makes sense,
רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir would say look it's true, it really all
comes through the signing, but you know what, that's going to lead
to sloppiness and all of the halachic requirements I will apply to
the writing as well. Okay, so maybe that's the position that you
care about the writing and the signing and that it is and
that it is
the signing is what you need from a תורה Torah perspective and
the writing is what and all of the demands in the writing
is from a rabbinic perspective. So the גמרא Gemara says one minute.
ואמר רב נחמן אומר היה רבי מאיר. ve-amar Rav Nachman omer haya
Rabbi Meir. רב נחמן Rav Nachman says that רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir
used
to. Okay, so somebody else who had your name and whose wife
had your wife's name, okay, of course the question is that as
you know it's a little funny because if you have two people
with the same names and same wife's names you might have to
be more specific in the גט. get. So it's a little question
how you could find the perfect named גט. get. But let's say
I don't know the סופר sofer was you know the סופר sofer
was practicing you know doing some classes or practicing writing a גט
get and he said John Doe divorced Jane Doe, but actually there
was a couple named John and Jane Doe and you happen to
find that גט. get. Okay? So the point is even if you
found a גט get in the garbage pail that happened to be
exactly right for you, okay, וחתמו ונתנו לה vechasmo u'nesano lah טופס
ד' אמות tofes daled amos and you signed and you had it
signed and gave it to your wife, always in the male voice
of course, כשר. kasher. It's כשר. kasher. Okay, so you see that
you know now maybe there's a little bit of like a בדיעבד
bedi'eved there or something, but it sounds like that he says it's
completely כשר. kasher. There is not even a Rabbinic requirement that the
writing follow any particular rules. וכי תימא v'chi teima and if you
say says the גמרא Gemara אנן בדאורייתא כמתנינן לה anan b'deoraisa kamasninin
lah that's only speaking at a Biblical level but maybe Rabbinically it's
invalid, where you really wouldn't say כשר kasher if it was invalid
Rabbinically, which is sort of what the גמרא Gemara says. אי הכי
ei hachi if that's true אומר היה רבי מאיר דבר תורה מיבעי
ליה. omer hayah Rebbe Meir devar Torah mibai lei. It should have
said רבי מאיר Rebbe Meir should have says as a from a
תורה Torah perspective it would even be כשר. kasher. But he's not
saying that. He's saying it would even be כשר kasher if you
did this. So clearly רבי מאיר Rebbe Meir even at a Rabbinic
level meaning maybe there's an idea of like לכתחילה lechatchila בדיעבד. bedi'eved.
But bottom line even at a Rabbinic level he does not demand
that the writing be done in any particular way. All of his
requirements focus on the signing. So there's no way for רבי מאיר
Rebbe Meir you would have to testify to how the writing was
done. Okay? Because no matter how the writing was done it would
be כשר. kasher. Okay, so we're still stuck. Who demands both the
writing and the signing? So the גמרא Gemara says אלא לעולם רבי
אלעזר היא. ela le'olam Rebbe Eliezer hi. Fine. It's רבי אלעזר. Rebbe
Eliezer. וכי לא בעי רבי אלעזר חתימה. v'chi lo bai Rebbe Eliezer
chasima. So now רבי אלעזר Rebbe Eliezer is the one who focuses
totally on the writing. He doesn't even need the גט get to
be signed. So why would you have to testify about how it
was signed? וכי לא בעי רבי אלעזר חתימה v'chi lo bai Rebbe
Eliezer chasima when is it true that רבי אלעזר Rebbe Eliezer does
not demand does not focus on does not require it to be
signed? That's true you don't have to sign it. But היכא דלא
איכא סהדי כלל heicha d'la ika sahedi klal if you didn't have
any witnesses signed, no problem. But והיכא דאיכא סהדי בעי. v'heicha d'ika
sahedi bai. If you are going to sign it, then he's going
to say okay you don't have to sign it. But if you
do sign it then you have to follow the rules. Okay now
how do you know that? What's the logic for that? דאמר רבי
אבא de'amar Rabbi Abba because רבי אבא Rabbi Abba said מודה רבי
אלעזר במזויף מתוכו שהוא פסול. modeh Rebbe Eliezer b'mezuyah mitocho shehu pasul.
רבי אלעזר Rebbe Eliezer would agree by something that is forged from
within that it's invalid. Now forged from within sort of means something
that has an intrinsic problem. Let's see how רש"י Rashi explains this.
רש"י Rashi says
במזויף מתוכו b'mezuyah mitocho five lines down in the narrow lines שחתם
עליו קרוב או פסול. shechasam alav karov o pasul. Let's say right
for example I'll give you an example. Somebody says to me Rabbi
Linzer I'm doing a wedding can I have as
you know as like what would be an example oh for witnesses
for the תנאים tna'im can I have non-כשר kasher witnesses sign the
תנאים? tna'im? Okay? Right? So I say look you don't have to
do the תנאים. tna'im. תנאים tna'im is just a vestige right we
תנאים tna'im don't mean anything anymore. You don't want to do the
תנאים tna'im be my guest. But if you're going to do the
תנאים tna'im and you're going to use a document then you don't
go ahead and do something that purports to be like a standard
כשר kasher document and you do it with non-כשר kasher עדים. edim.
Like I don't care if there isn't a document but don't do
it and do it in the wrong way. Okay? So that's what
רבי אלעזר Rebbe Eliezer says. If you don't want to sign it
be my guest. But if you are going to sign it you
can't sign it with non-כשר kasher עדים. edim. That's מזויף מתוכו. mezuyah
mitocho. You're putting the problem into the document. If you don't want
to have it don't have it. But don't do it and do
it in the wrong way. Now that's all very nice but what
does it have to do with לשמה? lishmah? לשמה lishmah is not
like it was like you know the who set it's like like
witnesses that are relatives or witnesses that are invalid are problematic witnesses.
So you don't sign problematic witnesses. But if you signed it without
לשמה lishmah that's only a problem if you demanded לשמה lishmah in
the first place. Whoever says that לשמה lishmah was even a concept
relevant to the signing for רבי אלעזר? Rebbe Eliezer? Is that clear?
Meaning רבי אלעזר Rebbe Eliezer does not demand it to be signed.
But conceptually signing is giving testimony. So if you're going to do
the signing you have to be classic testimony you have to have
כשר kasher witnesses. Right? But whoever said that not doing it לשמה
lishmah should ever be an issue? So the רש"י Rashi just throws
it in. He sneaks it in there או שלא לשמה. o shelo
lishmah. Okay? Or if you did שלא לשמה shelo lishmah that would
also be a problem for רבי אלעזר. Rebbe Eliezer. Which basically means
you know now תוספות Tosafot says look at תוספות Tosafot he raises
that question מודה רבי אלעזר במזויף מתוכו. modeh Rebbe Eliezer b'mezuyah mitocho.
מה עניין שלא לשמה למזוייף מתוכו שחתומים בו קרובים ופסולים? Mah inyan
shelo lishmah le-mezuya mi-tocho she-chosim bo krovim u-psulim? Right? How can you
compare then, right? A case of invalid witnesses, that that is a
problem—you didn't have to do it, but if you did it it's
a problem—to שלא לשמה? shelo lishmah? Cause there, some by invalid witnesses,
בדין נפסל, be-din nifsal, of course it's going to be invalid. משום
דילמא—now Mishum dilma he says another reason, like a secondary reason—דילמא אתי
למיסמך עליה להשיא ולהוציא ממון, dilma ati le-mismach aleih le-hasi u-le-hotzi mamon,
because you'll
miss—because if it's not kosher testimony, you'll wind up using the גט
get for testimony purposes to prove she's divorced to remarry or in
order for her to collect her כתובה. ketubah. Okay? But whatever, but
so he actually gives a very practical aspect. But the point is,
if you're signing witnesses, they have to be kosher. Okay? אבל הכא—I'm
Aval hacha skipping down where it says line starts with וכי עדים—אבל
הכא שעדים כשרים, kosher witnesses, אלא שחתמו שלא לשמה מה תקנה יש
בכך אם נסמוך עליהם? ela she-chasmu shelo lishmah mah takanah yesh be-kach
im nismach aleihem?
Who cares? Right? So there's—it's not transparent why you could say just
as you can't use kosher witnesses it has to be לשמה. lishmah.
If you don't have to sign all together then why when I
sign do I have to do it לשמה? lishmah? Okay? And then
he says like this, ויש לומר, ve-yesh lomar, four lines before the
end of that תוספות: Tosafot: דמכל מקום איכא למיגזר חתימה אטו כתיבה.
de-mickol makom ika le-migzar chasima atu ketiva.
Okay, so he gives an answer which is not at all as
interesting as מזוייף מתוכו. mezuya mi-tocho. It's like, once you're signing, we're
going to apply—sort of like what the גמרא Gemara said before for
רבי מאיר—once Rabbi Meir you're signing, we're going to apply the rules
to the writing to the signing, because if we have different rules
about the signing, you'll come to slip up around about the writing
as well. So it's really not a statement of, you know, of
מזוייף מתוכו, mezuya mi-tocho, some type of intrinsic, you know, invalidity that
you're inserting into the גט, get, but it's just, look, רבי אליעזר
Rabbi Eliezer does not require you to sign it. But if you
signed it, then there's at least a rabbinic requirement that everything be
done in the same way and follows the same rules. Okay, so
that's the גמרא's Gemara answer. Who is the opinion that requires both
the writing and the signing to follow לשמה lishmah demands? That is
רבי אליעזר. Rabbi Eliezer. He didn't need it to be signed, but
if it's signed, it's got to follow the same rules. Now I
want to suggest something a little more, like, you know, radical about
that. I'm sorry, I'm sorry, I got to remember to put this
on lock. Okay, I want to suggest—I
want to suggest
something a little more radical about that, which is, I remember I
mentioned to you before the question, which is why when רבי אליעזר
Rabbi Eliezer you do sign it, can you use those signatures? Right?
Meaning, you know, and we'll talk more about like what makes something
into a שטר shtar and so on. But it could be that
רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer says you don't need the signatures, but when
you put them in, right, the idea that you can now rely
on them and the woman could get remarried, they do actually become
even on a דאורייתא d'oraita level part of the גט. get. Meaning
דאורייתא d'oraita you don't need it, you could have the witnesses external,
but if you did put it on, then the תורה Torah recognizes
that as a גט get that has witnesses in it and that
has testimony in it, and the תורה Torah recognizes the meaning of
those witnesses. If you say that that's true, and there are ראשונים
Rishonim that say that, that according to רבי אליעזר, Rabbi Eliezer, when
the witnesses are put on, it's not just circumstantial evidence that there
were witnesses, it's like any classic שטר shtar that they are דאורייתא
d'oraita recognized as part of the גט. get. And therefore the גט
get can be used as evidence and as proof. Well if that's
true, maybe even at a דאורייתא d'oraita level once you put the
witnesses on, they actually do require the same—the same criteria as the
writing of the גט. get. Okay, so that is what the גמרא
Gemara is saying for רבי אליעזר. Rabbi Eliezer. You don't need the
witnesses, but if you put the witnesses on, then they actually are
going to require—have the same criteria as the writing of the גט.
get. תוספות Tosafot says that that's a rabbinic idea, you know, you
don't want one thing to slip up into the other thing, but
I'm suggesting that it could even possibly be a דאורייתא d'oraita requirement.
If you're going to have it, once you put it in, it
becomes part of the גט get and it requires the same criteria.
It makes sense not to have it, right? Well, not better for
the woman not to have it; she's going to need this גט
get to remarry. Okay, just be careful, follow the rules.
No, because you don't need the signatures, and if she's
fine she's divorced, but she's going to need them practically. She doesn't
need them for her legal status, but she's going to practically need
it. That's the תיקון עולם. tikkun olam. If she's going to want
to remarry, what's she going to do? Have to schlep these people
into court every time?
If there's—there's an עידי, eidei, right? Meaning—no, no, בית דין's Beis Din
not going to let her marry.
Of course not. You produce a piece of paper that you—you wrote
this at home? What—where's the evidence?
But מדאורייתא mi-d'oraita it works, then she can get married, right?
No, מדאורייתא mi-d'oraita it works but nobody knows about it.
I go ahead and I buy your car, your Jaguar, which I've
always had my eye on, right? And we do it in a—and
we do it in an alley and nobody knows about it, and
I don't bother to have any witnesses. דאורייתא D'oraita do I own
your car? Yes. Okay, am I going to be able to take
it if you deny that you ever sold it to me?
Well no, only if there's עידי. eidei.
No, no, no, forget you deny. Okay, I come to בית דין,
Beis Din, you're—it's parked in your garage. I come—you're not home, I
come to בית דין. Beis Din. They're not going to let me
do it either. Okay? They're
not going to let the woman remarry without evidence. She has a
status of an אשת איש. eshet ish. It's very nice that God
knows that she's
divorced— Doesn't matter, who's going to be the Rabbi, who's going to
be whatever? The society won't let her. How could you get married?
You were, how could you get remarried? You were married to this
other guy. I got divorced. How do you know? How can you
prove it? בית דין Bais Din won't let it. Any woman, I
don't understand, any woman can just say, oh of course I got
divorced, right?
And that's circumventing the, no, but then everyone's going to have a
גט. get.
It's not, so fine, go ahead, pay a סופר sofer five thousand
dollars to write a גט get but don't get it signed. Yes.
What's the purpose of having one without the witnesses signed?
The
purpose is, well, okay, A, you are divorced. So, okay, you go
somewhere they don't know you, you could get away with it. Maybe
you could find a place that they don't know your previous story,
so you don't need to prove it, okay? But you can't prove
it. Or that's the witnesses that are external to the גט get
that are seeing it, if you could שלעפ schlepp them into בית
דין, Bais Din, okay? Or if you're smart enough, so what you
do is right after you got the גט, get, you take those
witnesses and says, come with me to court, we're going to go
get this registered or something, okay? But the point is, that's תיקון
עולם. Tikkun Olam. All right? The תיקון עולם Tikkun Olam is is
that that's not always convenient, you don't always do that. It's better
to have a signed document right away.
Isn't it תיקון הקהילה דרבנן? tikkun hakehilla derabbanan? Here, you're sort of
basically not requiring it.
We're giving you the option. But it's an option you really want
to be taking. All right. You don't have to. Whatever we just
described to some cases you don't, but you want to be smart,
that's what you'll do. Okay. So now the גמרא Gemara says like
this. Okay. So the גמרא Gemara says like this, רב אשי אמר,
Rav Ashi amar, so that's our answer. And we've now very brilliantly
in the first דף, daf, second דף daf of the גמרא Gemara
introduced a major conceptual question about what makes something into a גט.
get. And we have one opinion that it's just the signing, one
opinion that it's just the writing, and one opinion that, well, it
is just the writing, but when you sign it, those signatures do
become part of the גט. get. Rabbinically or biblically, but they do
become it once you do get it signed. Okay. Now the גמרא
Gemara says,
רב אשי אמר הא מני רבי יהודה היא, Rav Ashi amar ha
mani Rabbi Yehuda hi, it's רבי יהודה. Rabbi Yehuda. דתניא רבי יהודה
אומר פוסל עד שתהא כתיבתו וחתימתו בתלוש. Detanya Rabbi Yehuda omer posel
ad shetehai ketivato vachatimato betalush.
רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda invalidates the גט get unless it's both written
and signed when it is not attached to the ground. Now, of
course, it's a funny case, because if it's written when it's not
attached, it's probably going to be signed when it is not attached,
but I guess you could imagine a case that I don't know,
I wrote it on something and then I planted it and let
the thing take root and then I signed it. Okay. So you
could theoretically imagine a case. So he says, anyway, it's a way
of saying this idea of מחובר mechubar is a way of saying
that the requirements apply to the writing and the signing. Now we
don't know conceptually what world is he coming from, right? Is he
saying you need to sign and I see and you need to
write? And but, you know, is he like a version of what
we said for רבי אלעזר? Rabbi Elazar? Or maybe he's his own
idea. Maybe he's saying that both of them combined make it a
גט. get. It's not either-or. You need to do both and they
both combined make it a גט get and the requirements apply throughout.
Okay. But there is now a nice third opinion. Okay. עד שתהא
כתיבתו וחתימתו בתלוש, Ad shetehai ketivato vachatimato betalush, both the signing and
the writing and the signing is when it is not attached to
the ground. So that's nice, כתיבה וחתימה. ketiva vachatima. So now the
גמרא Gemara says, well that was pretty obvious. מעיקרא מאי טעמא לא
מוקמינן לה כרבי יהודה? Meikara mai ta'ama lo mokminan lah keRabbi Yehuda?
So why don't we just jump to רבי יהודה? Rabbi Yehuda? Well,
that wouldn't have been fun, then we wouldn't have introduced to all
of us this important debate. But the גמרא Gemara isn't going to
say that. So why did we not just start with רבי יהודה?
Rabbi Yehuda? So the גמרא Gemara says, מהדרינן אדרבי מאיר, mahadarinan adaRabbi
Meir, because we would rather have said the משנה Mishna was רבי
מאיר, Rabbi Meir, דסתם משנה רבי מאיר, desetam Mishna Rabbi Meir, because
a סתם משנה stam Mishna is רבי מאיר, Rabbi Meir, and our
משנה Mishna is
anonymous. And therefore, we would rather the משנה Mishna had been a
רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir position because it would, our משנה, Mishna, הצריכו
שמו, hatzrichu shemo, well we'll get to that in a minute, the
named position. But the first statement that you have to say בפני
נכתב ובפני נחתם Bifnei nichtav uvifnei nechtam is an anonymous statement, so
we would rather it have been consistent with רבי מאיר. Rabbi Meir.
So that's why we tried to see if it was consistent with
רבי מאיר, Rabbi Meir, and we said no, רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir
only focuses on the signing. Now, מהדרינן אדרבי אלעזר, mahadarinan adaRabbi Elazar,
then we would also have liked it, then we tried to make
it go like רבי אלעזר, Rabbi Elazar, we would have liked that
to have happened, דקיימא לן הלכתא כוותיה בגיטין. dekaiyma lan hilchata kevateih
begittin. Okay. Now that's very important. We just laid out a super
fundamental debate, which has huge ramifications, and now the גמרא Gemara has
told us within
the same discussion how we פסקן. pasken. So Michael, you should be
very happy, because Michael's always, okay but how do we פסקן? pasken?
Okay. So it's really amazing in this right at the beginning, it's
very
well-structured first סוגיא, sugya, it introduces these fundamental ideas and even tells
us how we פסקן. pasken. We rule like רבי אלעזר, Rabbi Elazar,
at least by a גט. get. By other שטרות shtarot it's a
different discussion, but we rule that you really do not need the
signatures in the גט. get. The גט get could be כשר kasher
even if the witnesses are external and not signed. So we would
have liked it to have worked with רבי אלעזר, Rabbi Elazar, we
would have liked it to have worked according to the הלכה. halacha.
And therefore we delayed going to רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda who is
neither סתם משנה stam Mishna and neither the הלכה halacha that we
פסקן. pasken.
Okay. And that's where we are. Now of course it's a little
bit of a problem because while the משנה mishna is סתם, stam,
you have all these other תנאים, Tannaim, right? You have רבי אליעזר,
Rebbe Eliezer, you have רבי מאיר, Rebbe Meir, you have רבי יהודה.
Rebbe Yehuda. Right, so how does it work if the whole idea
of בפני נכתב ובפני נחתם bifnei nikhtav u-vifnei nehtam only works according
to רבי יהודה? Rebbe Yehuda? So one thing I'll say is this
is only a provisional explanation, we're actually going to change later, so
that's number one. But even at this stage, it goes back to
the point I was saying at the first stage, which is there's
a סתם משנה stam mishna and later תנאים Tannaim are really just
explaining the terms of the סתם משנה. stam mishna. So they don't
necessarily
themselves hold by... now it would be funny. What the גמרא Gemara
is really suggesting is if you ask רבי מאיר, Rebbe Meir, what
does the שליח shaliach have to say? רבי מאיר Rebbe Meir would
say oh he only has to say בפני נחתם. bifnei nehtam. And
if you would ask רבי אליעזר Rebbe Eliezer what does the שליח
shaliach have to say, unless you go the מזויף מתוכו mezuyaf mitokho
route, but at least initially the גמרא Gemara says oh according to
that he only has to say בפני נכתב, bifnei nikhtav, right? So
it's pretty funny that here they are explaining the conditions and the
requirements of a משנה mishna that they themselves don't even agree to
the requirement of both parts of the phrase. Okay? So it's a
real... it is a hard position. It seems very clear that all
the תנאים Tannaim demand both parts. So we're going to be revising
this idea. But at this stage we are saying
it's a רבי יהודה Rebbe Yehuda position who sees both the writing
and the signing as central to what makes it a גט. get.
Okay, so now we're going to take a look, so now what
have we done?
Let's think what we've done. We've laid out two explanations for what
the משנה mishna is. That was point number one. We analyzed the
question about how could you believe one witness? Logically you should need
two. How does this institution make sense at all? Then we went
ahead and we said, oh I'm sorry, before we even got there
we said two fundamental different explanations, למאי נפקא מינה. le-mai nafka mina.
What are some ramifications about it? Right? So it's just a beautiful
clearly presented... here's the debate, here are some theoretical נפקא מינא. nafka
minas. How does the institution work according to each side? Why do
you allow for one witness? Okay, how does both parts of the
phrase, בפני נכתב ובפני נחתם bifnei nikhtav u-vifnei nehtam, work according to
each side? Right? That's the next stage, that's central. And now we're
going to say let's look at the rest of the משנה mishna
and see how the rest of the משנה mishna plays out according
to these two approaches. Okay? So that's what we're going to do.
תנן, Tnan, we learned in our
משנה. mishna. רבן גמליאל אומר אף המביא מן הרקם ומן החגר.
Rabban Gamliel omer
af ha-mevi min ha-Rekem u-min ha-Hegar. Now we get, and now this
debate also allows us, not only is this trying to prove one
side of the debate, it's now going to allow us to analyze
what's going on in the rest of the משנה, mishna, because there
are debates in the משנה mishna about the criteria, right? About what
defines מדינת הים. medinat ha-yam. So you remember the first debate, right
as we said, right the first debate was it was a משנה
mishna said המביא גט ממדינת הים, ha-mevi get mi-medinat ha-yam, right? And
then you had three positions explaining what that term מדינת הים medinat
ha-yam meant. Right, what were those three positions? Okay, it says רבן
גמליאל אומר... Rabban Gamliel omer... מדינת הים medinat ha-yam is... אף המביא
מן הרקם ומן החגר. af ha-mevi min ha-Rekem u-min ha-Hegar. Okay, right?
And
then what's the next line?
רבן גמליאל אומר אף המביא מן הרקם ומן החגר, Rabban Gamliel omer
af ha-mevi min ha-Rekem u-min ha-Hegar, רבי אליעזר אומר אפילו
מכפר לודים ללוד. Rebbe Eliezer omer afilu mi-Kfar Ludim le-Lod. Okay, right?
מכפר לודים ללוד. mi-Kfar Ludim le-Lod. וחכמים אומרים, ve-Hakhamim omrim, right?
וחכמים אומרים, ve-Hakhamim omrim,
right? Okay, okay, anyway we'll get to חכמים Hakhamim in a minute.
But they say no, real מדינת הים. medinat ha-yam. Okay, now here
it is, מדינת הים medinat ha-yam sounds like far away, right? And
רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel and רבי אליעזר Rebbe Eliezer are saying no,
no, no, it doesn't have to be from far away, even close.
We don't exactly know the difference between רקם Rekem and חגר Hegar
and כפר לודים ללוד, Kfar Ludim le-Lod, but clearly they're saying even
close, and the חכמים Hakhamim are saying far away. So here's a
debate, here's a question. Why... what's the debate about? Why would one
opinion demand... say only when it's really far away and another opinion
say even when it's close? Okay, what is that debate about? And
maybe we can understand this debate through the different reasons that have
been put out about why to say בפני נכתב ובפני נחתם, bifnai
nichtav u-vifnai nechtam. right? Maybe it depends, why are you saying this?
Are you saying this because of witnesses? Are you saying this because
of לשמה? lishma? That might determine... that might help us understand what
this debate is about. So that's what we're going to do now.
Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says like this. תנן, Tnan, רבן גמליאל
אומר אף המביא מן הרקם ומן החגר. Rabban Gamliel omer af ha-mevi
min ha-Rekem u-min ha-Hegar. רבי אליעזר אומר אפילו מכפר לודים ללוד, Rebbe
Eliezer omer afilu mi-Kfar Ludim le-Lod, even from Kfar Ludim to Lod.
ואמר אביי, Ve-amar Abaye, now Abaye says, בעיירות הסמוכות לארץ ישראל ומובלעות
בתחום ארץ ישראל עסקינן. be-ayarot ha-semukhot le-Eretz Yisrael u-muvlaot bi-tehum Eretz Yisrael
askinan. Okay, places that are near ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael and swallowed
up in ארץ ישראל. Eretz Yisrael. Okay, so... and so what does
that mean? ואמר רבה בר בר חנה, Ve-amar Rabbah bar bar Hana,
לדידי חזי לי ההוא אתרא, le-didi hazei li ha-hu atra, I saw
that place, והויא כי מבי כובי לפומבדיתא. ve-havya ki mi-bei Kubi le-Pumbedita.
It was very short distance, it was like some Bei Kubi to
Pumbedita. to פומבדיתא. Pumbedita. Now, what does that mean? It means so
it says like this.
It says that רבן גמליאל, Rabban Gamliel, the way רש"י Rashi explains
it is, imagine, you know, here's you've got your boundary of Israel,
whatever. Okay, don't ask me to try and draw an Israel map.
Anyway, you've got your boundary. Okay, this is סמוכות. smuchot. It's a
city right near the border.
And רש"י Rashi says that's the position of רבן גמליאל, Rabban Gamliel,
even a city right near the border has to say. רבי אליעזר
Rabbi Eliezer goes further and he says even מובלעות. muvlaot. מובלעות muvlaot
would be something like this. And it's right there. It's sort of
like, can you see that? Right? It's like this.
Right? So it's near the border, but it's almost swallowed up. It's
like surrounded on multiple sides with Israel. Okay, so different degrees of
closeness. That's the debate. Okay, so now, now why are they saying
you have to say that close and the חכמים Chachamim or the
תנא קמא Tanna Kamma says only when it's farther away? So let's
take a look.
So מכלל, mikhla, it could actually be, yeah, that's true. מכלל דתנא
קמא סבר, mikhla de-Tanna Kamma savar, the תנא קמא Tanna Kamma is
of the opinion, הני לא צריך. hani lo tzarikh. No, no, no,
that close you don't have to. So what's that debate about? Whether
it's enough that it be just over the border line or does
it really have to be a distant location? So מאי לאו בהא
קמיפלגי? mai lav behai kamifligi? Is this a great way to explain
the debate in the משנה? Mishnah? דמר סבר, de-mar savar, one is
of the opinion, לפי שאין בקיאים בלשמה. lefi she-ein bekiyim b'lishmah. The
issue is, now let me before we even look, figure it out
for yourself. If the question were about the knowledge of לשמה, lishmah,
right, awareness of certain הלכות halachot etc. that they don't know about
outside of Israel, they know about in Israel, or if the issue
is about being able to find witnesses. So if something is just
over the border, according to which approach is that more of a
problem?
Witnesses or the לשמה? lishmah? You say לשמה? lishmah? Well, let me
reframe the question. What types of things are most affected by political
borders?
Right, travel, meaning cultural issues, knowledge of לשמה, lishmah, right, culture more
transcends borders, you know, political borders, you see a spectacle? Are you
skeptical?
What about if you have different education systems outside of the border
and...
oh, you're thinking about national education systems? I don't think the system
was that... okay. But cultural issues, let's say, let's say it was
a question about cuisine. Okay, would you think cuisine would be affected
necessarily by a narrow, like, by just a political border? Cultural things
more transcend borders, right? At least, I mean, far away, no, but
in the immediate environs, you're still within the same culture. But travel
is more obviously affected potentially by political borders. Anyway, that's... what? Then
distance? That's... no, distance is of course relevant, but when you're right
close and you're not distant, if you're distant everybody agrees that you
have to. Okay, but you're close but not distant, you're probably still
within the same culture, but it's, but it might be harder to
travel. And that's what the גמרא Gemara is saying.
And that's the surrounding...
and even more so if you're here. Okay, what here and here
are different degrees, but that's in contrast to way out here in
מדינת הים. Medinat HaYam. You're way out in מדינת הים, Medinat HaYam,
you clearly have problems both of witnesses and of the same knowledge
and the same culture, right? So you both have לשמה lishmah and
travel issues. But here, okay, you might have travel issues because you're
over the border, but if you're that close and certainly if you're
מובלע, muvla, you probably have the same general awareness, you're probably part
of the same culture. Okay.
Oh, I thought you were saying which of those two...
no, no, no, I'm sorry. I'm say- I'm saying between this and
that. Okay, this is a very hard... that's- this is like a
hair-splitting debate. Okay, but between this and that, okay, here you're going
to have a travel issue, but
you're- but you probably will not have a לשמה lishmah issue. Okay,
what's he do with that hair-splitting?
Well, we'll get to it.
Okay, מאי לאו בהא קמיפלגי? mai lav behai kamifligi? Is this what
they debate? דמר סבר לפי שאין בקיאים בלשמה, de-mar savar lefi she-ein
bekiyim b'lishmah, it's because of knowledge of לשמה, lishmah, והני גמירי. vehani
gemiri. Places that are close to Israel, even if they're on the
other side of the border, know the law. ומר סבר לפי שאין
עדים מצויין לקיימו, u-mar savar lefi she-ein edim metzuyin l'kayemo, and the
other's of the opinion that no, it's a problem about travel and
witnesses, והני נמי לא שכיחי. vehani nami lo shekhikhi. Once you're over
the border, you don't so always travel into the next country. Like
I said, you know, the cuisine might be affected, the knowledge might
be similar, but you don't ob- you don't easily travel into the
next country. So that's a great explanation, not doesn't explain this different,
but it's a great explanation of those- of that debate, מדינת הים
Medinat HaYam versus just over the border. So the גמרא Gemara says,
לא, lo, you don't have to say it that way. רבה מתרץ
טעמיה ורבא מתרץ טעמיה, Rabba metaretz ta'amei v'Rava metaretz ta'amei, each one
will explain it according to their own philosophy that it's only one
of these that's an issue. Let's start with לשמה. lishmah. רבה מתרץ
טעמיה, Rabba metaretz ta'amei, his reason, דכולי עלמא לפי שאין בקיאים בלשמה,
de-kuli alma lefi she-ein bekiyim b'lishmah, it's about לשמה lishmah and it's
about knowledge of הלכה. halacha. והכא בהא קמיפלגי, vehakha behai kamifligi, here's
the debate. תנא קמא סבר, Tanna Kamma savar, הני כיון דסמוכות מימר
גמירי. hani kivan de-smuchot mitmar gemiri. That's the obvious position. The תנא
קמא Tanna Kamma says, oh, it's... Only far away. These places that
are right on the border, they know the הלכה. halachah. ואתא רבן
גמליאל למימר, ve-ata Rabban Gamliel l'meimar, Rabban Gamliel says look, מובלעות גמירי,
muvla'ot gemiri, a place like this, okay, that's מובלעת, muvla'at, it's got,
you know,
everybody all around, like knows that. Okay, they're more likely to be
influenced by the culture and the knowledge. This place knows the הלכה.
halachah. I will not require from מובלעת. muvla'at. But סמוכות, semuchot, you
know, if it's not surrounded, might not be affected. And I'm going
to say that סמוכות semuchot might not actually know the הלכה. halachah.
Okay. ואתא רבן גמליאל למימר, ve-ata Rabban Gamliel l'meimar, look, מובלעות גמירי,
muvla'ot gemiri, I will concede that if it's מובלעת, muvla'at, they, we
can assume they know the הלכה. halachah. But סמוכות לא גמירי, ve-semuchot
lo gemiri, but just over the border, if you're not surrounded, I
really am concerned that they don't know the same הלכה. halachah. ואתא
רבי אליעזר. ve-ata Rabbi Eliezer. Now, what is רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer
going to say? Because רבי אליעזר, Rabbi Eliezer, you know, if you're
completely surrounded by the whole culture, how is it you don't know
the הלכה? halachah? ואתא רבי אליעזר למימר, ve-ata Rabbi Eliezer l'meimar, רבי
אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer says מובלעות נמי לא. muvla'ot nami lo. You are
not exempt if you're מובלעת, muvla'at, meaning you also have to say
it if you're מובלעת. muvla'at. Why? שלא תחלוק במדינת הים, shelo tachlok
bi-medinat ha-yam,
which is basically a way of saying לא פלוג. lo plug. It's
like, look, I am not going to try and figure out on
a case-by-case basis does this city, how much הלכה halachah does this
city know? We're going to send out SAT tests and we're going
to figure out and quiz everybody. Like, we have to make rules.
And the rules are going to be in Israel or out of
Israel. Okay? I'm not going to evaluate case-by-case whether a particular place
knows לשמה lishmah or doesn't know לשמה. lishmah. Very logical. You want
a legal system, you're going to have to make some concrete, simple,
quantifiable rules, even if they don't always exactly match up to what
your concerns are. So now the גמרא Gemara has explained that the
debate is that תנא קמא Tanna Kama says only distant places am
I really concerned about, nearby places I'm not concerned. רבן גמליאל Rabban
Gamliel says no, even nearby, it's not so obvious. There are some
places that it's fit to be concerned about, but I will concede
that some places are not a problem, even though they're over the
border. ורבי אליעזר ve-Rabbi Eliezer says we have to have a simple
rule. Simple rule is: anything over the border has to say לשמה,
lishmah, has to say בפני נכתב bifnei nikhtav ובפני נחתם. u-vifnei nehtam
Yeah, he's a formalist.
Yeah, a general rule, do you want to add? Yeah, because like
otherwise you take
the point at the top that it's surrounded by other cultures that
they know. Right. Exactly. And you say how מובלעת muvla'at is מובלעת
muvla'at and how
whatever, and like, just whatever, anything over the border line.
Okay. You won't cross the street in his neighbor's סוכה. sukkah. Exactly.
Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara says like this. Okay, בפלוגתא דרבה
ורבא. bi-pelugta de-Rabbah ve-Rava. Now, רבא Rava is going to be about,
about אין עדים מצויים לקיימו, ein edim metzuyim le-kaymo, about getting witnesses
and being able to validate their signatures. Okay, so that we require
when we're afraid that there won't be travel and that we won't
be able to have. Okay. So, דכולי עלמא אין עדים מצויים לקיימו.
de-chulei alma ein edim metzuyim le-kaymo. Everybody says that the problem is
because there are no witnesses. You can't get witnesses so easily. ותנא
קמא סבר הני כיון דסמוכות שכיחי. ve-Tanna Kama savar hani kivan de-semuchot
shechichi. That's good. תנא קמא Tanna Kama says look, nearby places, even
if they are over the political border, nearby places, there's enough travel
and they're nearby and we're not afraid about the ability to get
witnesses. So only far away places is it an issue. ואתא רבן
גמליאל למימר, ve-ata Rabban Gamliel l'meimar, רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel says מובלעות
שכיחי, סמוכות לא שכיחי. muvla'ot shechichi, semuchot lo shechichi. Same point. I'll
concede the point if it's מובלעת. muvla'at. If you're totally surrounded, there
will be travel. But if it's over the border and not surrounded,
there's not going to be so much travel. ואתא רבי אליעזר למימר
מובלעות נמי לא שכיחי שלא תחלוק במדינת הים. ve-ata Rabbi Eliezer l'meimar
muvla'ot nami lo shechichi shelo tachlok bi-medinat ha-yam. No, even if it's
מובלעת, muvla'at, it's, I agree you might be right, there might be
a lot of travel, but we have to be formalists, we have
to say לא פלוג, lo plug, we have to say anything over
the border requires. So basically the גמרא Gemara said that it came
from a fundamental, like, the first explanation was more satisfying, right? Oh,
the issue about close or far is a question about is it
לשמה lishmah or is it about עדים? edim? That's a really nice
explanation. But then says no, even if it's only about one idea,
לשמה, lishmah, or only about עדים, edim, you know, there's a question
about where do you draw the line? How much of a לשמה
lishmah problem do you need before you start saying it, or how
much are you a formalist and you say it as soon as
you cross the border line? So within any type of an issue
we could all debate, we could all agree on the principle and
debate the particulars. So we could all agree it's לשמה, lishmah, we
could all agree it's אין עדים מצויים לקיימו, ein edim metzuyim le-kaymo,
and we still debate is that going to, are we going to
demand that even by places that are nearby? And that's the debate
going on in the משנה. Mishnah. Yes, it's a very powerful methodological
sort of principle. In other words, in a legal system, when is
it appropriate not to be nuanced? Right. When do you context, right,
when are you formalist and when are you contextual? I mean, the
vast majority of the time, we're formalists, because you can't have a
legal system that you're evaluating everything on a case-by-case basis. Okay. So
now the גמרא Gemara says like this. Now, פא... pa... what? Okay,
I've missed that. Okay, אוקיי, תנן. okay, t'nan. Now let's go to
the next stage of the משנה. Mishnah. וחכמים אומרים. ve-Chachamim omrim. Now
we were comparing these two to the תנא קמא. Tanna Kama. And
the תנא קמא Tanna Kama just said מדינת הים, Medinat Ha-Yam, and
they're explaining it, but we were seeing תנא קמא Tanna Kama as
a, as a different opinion. Now we... and as saying far away.
Now the חכמים Chachamim seem to say the same thing. The חכמים
Chachamim say אינו צריך שיאמר בפני נכתב ובפני נחתם אלא המביא ממדינת
הים, eino tzarich sheyomar bifnai nichtav uvifnai nechtam ela hamevi mimedinat hayam,
but then it has the word והמוליך. vehamolich. Okay, and the question
was, was מוליך molich back to the תנא קמא, Tanna Kamma, or
was that part of what the חכמים Chachamim said? Okay, but let's
take a look now what the גמרא Gemara does with that. Okay,
so the גמרא Gemara says like this: תנן, tnan, let's go to
the next page of the משנה. Mishnah. וחכמים אומרים אינו צריך שיאמר
בפני נכתב ובפני נחתם אלא המביא ממדינת הים והמוליך. Vechachamim omrim eino
tzarich sheyomar bifnai nichtav uvifnai nechtam ela hamevi mimedinat hayam vehamolich. מכלל,
Michlal, so now it's going to focus on מוליך. molich. It's saying
that מוליך molich is the words of the חכמים, Chachamim, and it's
going to say that that is what the חכמים Chachamim are introducing.
So they're now introducing a new idea, that you have to say
it not only when you come from חוץ לארץ Chutz La'aretz to
ישראל, Yisrael, but even from ישראל Yisrael to חוץ לארץ. Chutz La'aretz.
Now that seems perfect for this debate, right? Think for a minute.
If it's about לשמה, lishmah, do you have to say it when
you're going from ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael to חוץ לארץ? Chutz La'aretz?
Pay attention people, no! Because it's about that they don't know out
in the, out in the boondocks they don't know, but if you're
going from ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael to חוץ לארץ, Chutz La'aretz, you
don't have to say it. But if it's about travel, would you
have to say it? Yes! What, if you travel one direction, travel
the other direction, right?
So that's a great question. So the חכמים Chachamim are saying you
have to say it when you go out, and the others are
not. What's that debate about? Sounds like it's this debate.
וחכמים אומרים אינו צריך שיאמר בפני נכתב ובפני נחתם אלא המביא ממדינת
הים, Vechachamim omrim eino tzarich sheyomar bifnai nichtav uvifnai nechtam ela hamevi
mimedinat hayam, when you bring it, והמוליך, vehamolich, or if you bring
it out to, to מדינת הים. Medinat Hayam. מכלל, Michlal, from this
you can infer דתנא קמא סבר מוליך לא צריך, deTanna Kamma savar
molich lo tzarich, that that the you don't have to bring it,
you
know, say it when you go out.
So what's that debate about? מאי לאו בהא קמיפלגי? Mai lav beha
kamiflagi? This seems to be the debate. דמר סבר לפי שאין בקיאין
לשמה, Demar savar lefi she'ein beki'in lishmah, one is of the position
that it's about לשמה, lishmah, והני גמירי, vehanei gemiri, and of course
they know in ארץ ישראל, Eretz Yisrael, so you only have to
say it when you're coming from חוץ לארץ. Chutz La'aretz. ומר סבר,
Umar savar, and the other holds, לפי שאין עדים מצויין לקיימו. lefi
she'ein edim metzuyin lekaymo. No, it's about the presence of עדים, edim,
the prevalence of עדים. edim. And therefore והני נמי לא שכיחי. vehanei
nami lo shechichi. So it's also, people from חוץ לארץ Chutz La'aretz
aren't often visiting, people from, the same way people from חוץ לארץ
Chutz La'aretz aren't often visiting ארץ ישראל, Eretz Yisrael, the same is
true in inverse. Of course now we've got the opposite. People from
חוץ לארץ Chutz La'aretz always visit ארץ ישראל, Eretz Yisrael, but not,
well, depends if you're on your year off after the army. Anyway.
Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says like this, so anyway, what? Is
רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer saying you only need the witness for the
signing? I'm sorry? What about the... does רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer say?
We're ignoring that earlier רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer ורבי מאיר veRabbi Meir
debate. Let's not worry about that right now. Okay, we're now focusing
on just the רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer of the משנה. Mishnah. All
right, so the גמרא Gemara says like this, so anyway, it seems
like the question of whether you have to say it when you're
going out of ישראל Yisrael is exactly the question of לשמה lishmah
or לפי שאין עדים מצויין לקיימו. lefi she'ein edim metzuyin lekaymo. So
the גמרא Gemara says: No, we're going to make it work according
to each approach. רבה מתרץ לטעמיה ורבא מתרץ לטעמיה. Rabbah metaretz leta'amei
veRava metaretz leta'amei. Each one explains it according to their reason. רבה
מתרץ לטעמיה Rabbah metaretz leta'amei that it's about לשמה. lishmah. Now if
it's about לשמה, lishmah, what's the logic that you have to say
it in the opposite direction? So the גמרא Gemara says דכולי עלמא
לפי שאין בקיאין לשמה והכא בגזירת מוליך אטו מביא קמיפלגי. dekouli alma
lefi she'ein beki'in lishmah vehacha begezerat molich atu mevi kamiflagi. This is
sort like ramping it up one stage from being a formalist. We're
not only going to be a formalist, but we're going to extend
the formalism and make it symmetrical. So we're going to say since
you always have to say it when you come from out of
ישראל Yisrael into ישראל, Yisrael, we're going to be consistent and say
you have to say it when you go from ישראל Yisrael to
out of ישראל. Yisrael. Okay. So therefore, because if you only require
it in one direction, that'll people get confused. Exactly. דתנא קמא... now
the funny thing is, who are you afraid is going to get
confused? If this is all being overseen by a בית דין, Beit
Din. you know, and they're, of course you might be able to
deliver it before witnesses and not a בית דין. But I mean,
once גיטין gittin start getting rejected, but okay, you don't want somebody
to have schlepped all the way. Somebody will say, what do you
mean? I saw a guy come from ארץ ישראל, Eretz Yisrael, he
brought a גט, get, he didn't have to say anything.
So I'm delivering this גט get and I'm not saying anything. You
know, sorry buddy, right?
So I mean,
so you know, that's going to be a problem.
So we might as well just have it always to require it.
יעל, Yael, you want to set an example so that they understand.
Right, if you're worried about their education. Exactly, exactly. And if they
don't know so much in מדינת הים, Medinat Hayam, and everybody who's
coming from ישראל Yisrael is saying it, that's also a good right,
exactly, you're setting a good example. Okay. דתנא קמא סבר לא גזרינן
מוליך אטו מביא. deTanna Kamma savar lo gazrinan molich atu mevi. No,
we're not afraid that if you, that sending it out will lead
to bringing it in. We don't require it sending it out, but
we do require it when it's coming in. ורבנן סברי גזרינן מוליך
אטו מביא. Verabbanan savri gazrinan molich atu mevi. No, in principle we
should only need it when you're bringing it into ישראל, Yisrael, but
we're going to make a גזירה gezerah and say you're also going
to demand it when you bring it out of ארץ ישראל. Eretz
Yisrael. Okay, we're going to have a similar type of a requirement.
So therefore, so nobody will get confused. It'll always get done. That's
how רבה Rabbah explains it. He has to make a גזירה, gezerah,
there's no intrinsic reason why it should be required. Let's take a
look at רבא. Rava. ורבא מתרץ לטעמיה. Verava metaretz leta'amei. רבא Rava
explains according to his reason. דכולי עלמא לפי שאין עדים מצויין לקיימו.
dekouli alma lefi she'ein edim metzuyin lekaymo. It's a problem about getting
witnesses. Okay, now, so if it's a problem about getting witnesses, it
should be obvious you need it in both directions, right? So how
could a תנא, Tanna, how could somebody say you only need it
going and not, and in the opposite way? Now I want to
say parenthetically there might be a good explanation which the גמרא Gemara
isn't saying, which is that we actually... You know, there was, I
mean, there's travel both from ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael to בבל Bavel
and בבל Bavel to ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael for תלמוד תורה, Talmud
Torah, but it seems it was more from ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael
to בבל Bavel that they were traveling for תלמוד תורה, Talmud Torah,
the בבל Bavel that the תורה Torah was stronger in בבל, Bavel,
although it was in both directions. So anyway, it's sort of like
now, except like I was sort of saying now, now more of
the travel is from חוץ לארץ Chutz La'aretz to ארץ ישראל. Eretz
Yisrael. I mean people have to go back home, but that doesn't
matter, if you've got to find the witness, you're going to need
constant, you'll need a large number of people constantly coming, right, to
your place. So if you want to be able to identify the
witnesses. So it could be that the תנא קמא Tanna Kamma held
that it's about witnesses and the reason you only need it when
you're going in one direction, like is it the opposite? No, you
need it when the witnesses, when the guy's coming in, because there's
not so much travel into Israel. But you don't need it when
it's going out because maybe there is a lot of travel out
of Israel. You could in theory say that, but the גמרא's Gemara
not going to say it. Once it's about travel and witnesses, presumably
you should need it in both directions. And the גמרא's Gemara going
to say, so you know what, רבנן בתראי לפרושי טעמא דתנא קמא
הוא דאתו. Rabbanan Batrai le-frushei taama de-Tanna Kamma hu de-atu. The second
רבנן Rabbanan when they say המוליך, ha-molich, they're really just explaining when
we said המביא, ha-meivi, we didn't just mean המביא. ha-meivi. We meant
whether it was המביא meivi or המוליך, molich, which by the way,
that phrase לפרושי טעמא דתנא קמא le-frushei taama de-Tanna Kamma goes to
exactly what I was saying was going on in the משנה. Mishnah.
We had an early statement, המביא גט ממדינת הים, ha-meivi get mi-medinat
ha-yam, and you had a debate what the terms of that statement
meant. כפר עכו, Kfar Akko, כפר לודים ללוד, Kfar Ludim le-Lud, no
it literally means מדינת הים. medinat ha-yam. So you know what, the
גמרא's Gemara saying there's a similar debate about what words mean. There's
not only a debate about what מדינת הים medinat ha-yam means, there's
a debate about what the word המביא ha-meivi means. Is it דוקא
המביא davka meivi the same way, is it really only מדינת הים
medinat ha-yam or any place over the border? So when we say
המביא, ha-meivi, is it means only המביא, ha-meivi, right, only when you're
coming in, or does it even mean when you're going out? Okay,
so that's what the גמרא Gemara is saying, that really if it's
about עדים, edim, then it is whether you're coming in or going
out. And when the חכמים Chachamim add המוליך, ha-molich, they're not debating.
They're just clarifying that you really require it in both directions. Okay?
So everybody good? Okay. So some of the debates in the משנה
Mishnah could be explained nicely depending on whether it's about עדים edim
or about לשמה. lishmah. But the גמרא Gemara has said there's ways
you can take one position and explain it. The question about where,
how far away, how near, could just be a question of degree.
And the question about המביא meivi versus המוליך molich could either be
a question about do we want to just be parallel and consistent
so you shouldn't confuse it, or are we clarifying that everybody agrees
you need it in both directions and we were just clarifying. Yes.
Since it's been bothering me about the לשמה lishmah side, if the
תורה Torah was stronger in בבל, Bavel, why is ארץ ישראל Eretz
Yisrael privileged over בבל? Bavel? Right, so you know what? So you're
right. So you're right. And what I said before, just strike what
I said before because even if it's true in terms of בבל,
Bavel, the מדינת הים medinat ha-yam is not בבל. Bavel. מדינת הים
medinat ha-yam is the diaspora, is the places where are not a
lot of Jews living, not so learning. בבל Bavel is not standard
מדינת הים. medinat ha-yam. Okay, and the גמרא's Gemara going to get
to that later, that בבל Bavel has a special status. But conceptually,
you know, מדינת הים medinat ha-yam are the far-flung communities, okay, not
the major center of בבל. Bavel. We'll get to בבל Bavel later.
So I shouldn't have given that example. Okay, so let's take a
look. גמרא Gemara says like this: תנן המביא גט ממדינה למדינה במדינת
הים. Tnan, ha-meivi get mi-medina lim-medina be-medinat ha-yam. Let's keep on going
in the משנה. Mishnah. Okay, and now this isn't even debated. So
this is going to be a test for which position makes sense.
So you've got a position that says if you bring from one
מדינה medina to another מדינה medina in מדינת הים, medinat ha-yam, okay.
So you're here and you're bringing from France to Spain. Where's France?
Whatever. Is that good? Okay, I better not show how bad is
my geography and my drawing skill. Anyway, fine. I know what Spain
sort of looks like. Anyway, so you're bringing from this, I know
if that's Germany or France, anyway, so you're bringing from מדינה medina
to מדינה medina in מדינת הים medinat ha-yam you have to say.
Okay, so that's what the משנה Mishnah says, okay? So what can
we infer from this? Now, does when you're bringing from מדינה medina
to מדינה medina in מדינת הים, medinat ha-yam, does it have a
לשמה lishmah problem? Yes. Does it have an עדים מצויים לקיימו edim
metzuyim lekaymo problem? Depends on well, okay, but assuming right, but if
they're different מדינות medinot we'll assume yes, okay? We'll assume any different
מדינה medina yes. So clearly you have to say it's got both
problems. Let's see what the גמרא Gemara says about this. Okay. המביא
גט ממדינה למדינה במדינת הים צריך שיאמר בפני נכתב ובפני נחתם. Ha-meivi
get mi-medina lim-medina be-medinat ha-yam tzarich she-yomar bifnai nechtav u-vifnai nechtam. הא
באותה מדינה במדינת הים, Ha be-ota medina be-medinat ha-yam, but it sounds
like if you had stayed within one מדינה medina in מדינת הים,
medinat ha-yam, it sounds like לא צריך, lo tzarich, you wouldn't. Now
one minute. I get the travel issue there, but there's still a
לשמה lishmah problem. So לרבא ניחא, le-Rava nicha, that's good for לרבא.
Rava. לרבה קשיא. le-Rabbah kashya. So I get why if it's all
within Spain, I get why you don't have to, it's not a
problem of signatures, but I don't get why you're not concerned about
לשמה. lishmah. So the גמרא Gemara says: לא תימא הא באותה מדינה
במדינת הים לא צריך. Lo teima ha be-ota medina be-medinat ha-yam lo
tzarich. No, no, you misread it. The implication here is not within
one מדינה medina you don't need. Even within one מדינה medina you
do need. So if even within one מדינה medina you do need,
why do you say from מדינה medina to מדינה? medina? אלא אימא
מדינה למדינה בארץ ישראל לא צריך. Ela eima medina lim-medina be-Eretz Yisrael
lo tzarich. It's to come and te... you if you're in מדינת
הים, Medinas ha-Yam, you have to say it from מדינה medina to
מדינה. medina. But if you're in ארץ ישראל, Eretz Yisrael, and it's
between like, you know, יהודה Yehuda and גליל, Galil, מדינה למדינה, medina
l'medina, then you don't need to say it, because it's really about
לשמה. lishma. So if it's about לשמה, lishma, it's true, even in
one מדינה medina you have to say it, but we're saying מדינה
למדינה medina l'medina you have to, so you should infer from it.
Of course, the logical thing to see is, to infer is that
one מדינה medina you don't have to. But what the גמרא Gemara
is saying is no, one מדינה medina you do, but we're saying
מדינה למדינה medina l'medina you do to infer that מדינה למדינה medina
l'medina in ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael you don't. Since it's all about
לשמה, lishma, you don't. Well wait, let's go a little further. Okay,
לא צריך. lo tzarich. So the גמרא Gemara says, wait a minute,
הא בהדיא קתני לה. ha ba-hedya katani lah. That's explicit in the
משנה. Mishna. המביא גט בארץ ישראל אינו צריך לומר בפני נכתב ובפני
נחתם, Ha-mevi get b'Eretz Yisrael eino tzarich lomar be-fanai niktav u-ve-fanai nechtam,
which sounds like you never have to say it in Israel, the
land of Israel. The גמרא Gemara says no, אי מההיא הוה אמינא,
ee me-hahi hava amina, if it was that I would say, הני
מילי דיעבד, hani mili di-avad, that's only post-facto, which I don't know
why I would have said that, אבל לכתחילה לא, aval l'chatchila lo,
קא משמע לן. ka mashma lan. Oh, so that's pretty weak. Okay,
it seems pretty clear in the משנה. Mishna. The obvious thing to
infer here is that the same מדינה medina you do not have
to say it, but the גמרא Gemara is saying no, no, no,
that's not true, you do have to say it, it's about לשמה,
lishma, it's just to tell you that ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael you're
totally golden. Okay, that's רבא's Rava approach, but רבא Rava is now
clearly getting out on a limb. Okay, רבא Rava is the one
that's looking a little hard, a little more suspicious. Now let's take
a look. ואיכא דמותיב לה הכי, v'ika d'motiv lah hachi, some ask
it in the reverse. הא ממדינה למדינה בארץ ישראל לא צריך, ha
m'medina l'medina b'Eretz Yisrael lo tzarich, which is again not the obvious
inference. אהא, aha, from one מדינה medina to another you have to,
which suggests that here from one מדינה medina to another מדינה medina
you don't. Now what's the logic about that if it's about travel?
So the גמרא Gemara says לרבא ניחא, l'Rava nicha, for רבא Rava
you understand why you don't between let's say יהודה Yehuda and גליל
Galil in ארץ ישראל, Eretz Yisrael, it's all about לשמה, lishma, אבל
לרבה קשיא. aval l'Rabbah kashya. But if it's about עדים, edim, then
it should be a problem, who cares whether it's Israel or not
Israel? It should all be about one מדינה medina to another. There
really should be no special status of Israel all together. Israel should
be irrelevant. It's מדינה medina to מדינה, medina, right? I mean that's
really the question to ask, which is according to רבה, Rabbah, who
cares about Israel? Who cares about the land of Israel? It's all
about מדינה medina to מדינה. medina. So why does the משנה Mishna
sound, so the better way to frame this is not from a
דיוק, diyuk, the better way to frame this is why does the
משנה Mishna say in the land of Israel you never have to
say? What ever happened to the problem of travel and the problem
of מדינה medina to מדינה? medina? Who cares about whether it's in
the land of Israel or not in the land of Israel? So
the גמרא Gemara says no, לא תימא ממדינה למדינה בארץ ישראל לא
צריך. lo teima m'medina l'medina b'Eretz Yisrael lo tzarich. Don't say from
one מדינה medina to another you don't have to, because you do
have to, it's actually claiming in from one מדינה. medina. אלא אימא
הא באותה מדינה במדינת הים לא צריך. ella eima ha b'osa medina
b'medinas ha-yam lo tzarich. No, what it's saying is that when you're
within Spain you don't have to say, because it's all about travel.
So the גמרא Gemara is saying one minute, so what are you
trying to tell me? הא ממדינה למדינה בארץ ישראל מאי? צריך. ha
m'medina l'medina b'Eretz Yisrael mai? tzarich. So wait, let me get this
straight רבה. Rabbah. You're telling me that you're saying that in the
land of Israel from one מדינה medina to another you do have
to say? I mean I get why that fits your position, but
you know, but the משנה Mishna says in Israel you don't have
to say. מתני המביא ממדינה למדינה סתם. matni ha-mevi m'medina l'medina stam.
Don't make it about Israel, say when you bring from one מדינה
medina to another you have to. Okay, so clearly in Israel from
one מדינה medina to another מדינה medina you don't have to, right?
Because it says מדינה medina to מדינה medina in מדינת הים. Medinas
ha-Yam. According to you רבה, Rabbah, it should just say מדינה medina
to מדינה. medina. Why does ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael make a difference?
So the גמרא Gemara says you're right, fine. לעולם ממדינה למדינה בארץ
ישראל נמי לא צריך. le-olam m'medina l'medina b'Eretz Yisrael nami lo tzarich.
You know what, you're right. I can see the point. It's pretty
explicit in the משנה. Mishna. From one מדינה medina to another in
ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael you don't have to say it. Now how
am I going to justify that if it's based on עדים? edim?
Here's how I'm going to justify it. לא צריך, lo tzarich, דכיון
דאיכא עולי רגלים, d'keivan d'ika olei regalim, because you know what, within
the land of Israel the difference of one מדינה medina to another
is not big. Is there יהודה? Yehuda? Is there גליל? Galil? Fine.
There's a lot of travel within the land of Israel. דכיון דאיכא
עולי רגלים, d'keivan d'ika olei regalim, people come up for the for
רגל, regel, משכח שכיחי mishkach shechichi there are a lot of people
at least in one direction. Travel, there's a lot of travel. All
right, but it doesn't really, it's one direction travel, but okay, fine.
Yeah, but you don't get, so it doesn't work both ways. Anyway,
the גמרא Gemara says one minute, תינח בזמן שבית המקדש קיים. teinach
bi-zman she-Beis HaMikdash kayam. That's good when there's a בית המקדש, Beis
HaMikdash, right? You're saying the משנה Mishna was written only for the
time the בית המקדש? Beis HaMikdash? בזמן שאין בית המקדש קיים מאי
איכא למימר? bi-zman she-ein Beis HaMikdash kayam mai ika l'meimar? How about
no בית המקדש?
Beis HaMikdash? כיון דאיכא בתי דינין דקביעי, keivan d'ika batei dinin d'keviei,
משכח שכיחי. mishkach shechichi. Yes, because there are fixed courts and
again I don't know why fixed courts mean, I guess people travel
and presumably in like ירושלים Yerushalayim or whatever was more of a
center, and they had fixed courts, so people more travel to the
center and therefore there would be a lot of travel. Now I
do have to still tell you travel doesn't necessarily mean it's equal
in both directions, so it's not so obvious when I'm going to
ירושלים Yerushalayim out to some distant village why they don't say בפני
נכתב be-fanai niktav because you're that distant village is never going to
see somebody else from ירושלים Yerushalayim for another. 10 years, you know.
So it's like it's one thing people coming in, but you could
say anyway whatever, it doesn't exactly, you have to sort of figure
out how it makes sense how travel in one direction can allow
this problem to be
solved, but the גמרא's Gemara basic answer is you're right, it sounds
like there's special status to ארץ ישראל, Eretz Yisrael, but we're not
going to explain it based on לשמה. lishma. We're going to explain
it based on עדים מצויים לקיימו. eidim metzuyim lekaymo. So at this
stage we've worked through the basis of the משנה, Mishnah, we've worked
through most of the other statements of the משנה, Mishnah, we're not
done, we'll continue with that, and although some of them seem to
fall very neatly on the lines of עדים eidim or לשמה, lishma,
we're able to explain how they can be made sense consistently with
one approach, and we'll continue with this tomorrow.